let's look at the solution
to our three height reduction quiz we
had this code and we are trying to
transform it through three height
reduction into something that minimizes
the overall number of cycles it takes to
execute this code here the code takes
six cycles to do because each of the
instructions depends on the previous one
now when doing three height reduction
what we need to do is really figure out
what is the expression that this is
trying to compute and then rewrite that
expression so here's what we have here
we have r1 plus r2
put the result in r10 then subtract r3
then add our 4 then subtract our five
then add our six
then subtract our seven so this is what
we are trying to compute how do we
compute it with three height reduction
well the idea is to compute
r1 and r2 that's what we're doing here
and then compute
the rest of the things and then add them
up in a tree so here what we need to do
is we need to add up four numbers and
then subtract
three numbers from that so first we will
add up the four numbers we already added
up r1 and r2
now we're going to add up r4 and r6 next
the result of the two additions
are gonna be
combined
so we're going to add up what we have
for r1 and r2 and what we have for r4
and r6 so now in r10 we have the r1 plus
r2 plus r4 plus r6
now we're going to subtract r3 r5 and r7
from it if we do it one at a time
that's going to be slow so what we're
going to do is we're going to
add up r3 r5 and r7 and then subtract
that from our r10 that's why we have two
adds here so clearly what we're doing
here is we're simply adding up r3
r5
and then r7 is added to that
so this needs to be r11 so now r11 has
r3 plus r5 plus r7
and now we subtract that from
r10
and we get the final answer in r10 now
let us see how many cycles we need to do
this to do that let's draw the
dependencies here we have the dependence
again
like this
so each instruction needed to be done
right after the previous one is done
here there is no dependence between
these two
there is a dependence here
and here so the third instruction needs
to wait for the first two to complete
there is now no dependence here so this
one can be done right away even though
it's the fourth instruction in our code
and then there is a dependence here
and then finally there is a dependence
here and also our final r10 here needs
to be brought this way so if you look at
what can be done in the first cycle this
can be done in the first cycle and so
can this this cannot because it has to
wait
this can
so this is also done in the first cycle
and then this has to wait for that and
so on
so in our first cycle we've already done
three instruction half of the
instructions that we had in the second
cycle we can do this because these two
complete in the first cycle
we can do this because it only waits for
this and that's been done and finally in
the third cycle we have to do this
because it has to wait for the results
of the second cycle so we have completed
our six instructions now in three cycles
and we got an ilp of two which is twice
as good as we had before the three
height reduction